HUSSAIN MANSOOR

Dubai, UAE | +971-5019-33152

https://www.linkedin.com/in/husyn/ – https://husyn.dev hussainmansoorraj@gmail.com

https://bit.ly/2XkaEG6

https://bit.ly/3s0Jmm7

https://bit.ly/3nlNLfVhttps://bit.ly/38ifVny

https://bit.ly/3pt6bgM

DELIVERY FOCUSED SOFTWARE ARCHITECT | TEN+ YEARS' EXPERIENCE

CUTTING DEVELOPMENT TIME AND COSTS, IMPROVING PERFORMANCE AND ENHANCING SERVICE

Software Engineer and Architect who combines deep technical knowledge with a passion for high-quality software in diverse industry settings, including telecommunications and marketing. Defines application architecture while facilitating rapid development through awareness of the full project and Software Development Life Cycle (SDLC); champions a focus on stability and performance, including analysis and optimisation across multiple platforms, automation and reducing toil. Leads requirements management and business case development (to highlight solutions feasibility) alongside data analysis and reporting. Enjoys maintaining awareness in emerging technologies, including developments in cloud computing and microservices.

CERTIFICATIONS

AWS Certified Solutions Architect (Associate)
AWS Certified Developer (Associate)
Scrum.org Professional Scrum Master
Scrum.org Professional Scrum Developer
PagerDuty Certified Incident Responder

CORE COMPETENCIES

Solutions Development | Architecture Development | SCRUM Methodologies

Team Leadership, Training and Mentoring | Project Scoping and Management | Technical Problem Solving

Interpersonal Communication | Automation | Client Engagement

Cost Reduction Initiatives | Process Enhancements | Performance Optimisation | System Rollout

TECHNOLOGIES

Databases: Redis | MSSQL | MySQL | AWS Aurora | DynamoDB | PostgreSQL

Languages: JSON | YML | Python | Java | Swift | Kotlin | JavaScript

Testing / Tracking: Postman | Selenium | JIRA | Apache JMeter | Locust | Others **Server:** Glassfish | IIS | TeamCity | SonarQube | NGINX | APACHE

Architecture: RESTful API Design | Microservices | SOA | Event driven | Monoliths | Cloud Native

Version Control: Git | SVN | Bitbucket | GitHub

Cloud: Amazon Web Services (AWS) | Private Cloud

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE AND ACHIEVEMENTS

EMIRATES AIRLINES GROUP (LINNK GROUP)

Senior Solutions Architect

December 2021-Present

Working under the portfolio of financial systems for Emirates Group. Helping the Scrum team achieve scalability, security and quality non-functional requirements. Following Solutions Architecture practices like Design Reviews, documenting Solutions Intents, presenting engineering solutions to stakeholders while keeping the cost, complexity and budgets under consideration.

AIRLIFT TECHNOLOGIES

Engineering Manager 2021-2021

Helping the engineering team to adopt Agile mindset and Scrum practices with respect to Microservices Architecture. Continuously working towards bringing the maturity in Cloud Management and Systems Engineering practices to follow Architecture guiding principles. Given the high-scale requirements, strategically defining a case to migrate to Kubernetes with continuous deployments behind feature-flagged environments to achieve high velocity delivery with robustness and quality.

Key achievements

Page 1 of 3

- Played key role in introducing, training and ensuring right Agile mindset in software delivery. Totally eliminated weekend work, late night builds and such practices with means of streamlined processes.
- Introduced the concept of **Systems Engineering** and Google's **SRE Framework** to improve the product quality in engineering team. Creating a culture of design and Architecture reviews to ensure right direction of systems.
- Initiated migration of legacy system from Silo to **Microservices architecture** for agility and maintainability.
- Created a case for **Multi-Account AWS setup** given the challenges of security blast radius, service limits in cloud and segregation of concerns issue with single account.
- Managed to acquire Pakistan's first **Private Pricing contract** with AWS to get 7% discount on bills and 30k USD in credits discount.
- Planning and implementing right **design patterns of distributed systems** like Circuit Breaker, Exponential Backoff, Centralised Logging, etc. to improve system's reliability and observability.

REA GROUP ASIA

Lead Systems Engineer (promoted from Senior Systems Engineer in 2020)

2019-2021

Recognised for combination of business empathy and technical expertise to translate ideas from concept into reliable and scalable products. I worked in fast-paced dynamic environments while continuously overseeing and improving critical infra projects within this digital company.

Facilitate full application development life cycle management, including analysis, technical requirements gathering, design, coding, testing, implementation and support for Malaysia's number one property marketing company.

Key achievements

- Played key role in seamless transition of traditional application architecture to **Microservices architecture** built on Nodejs.
- Configured build pipelines and setup Bash scripts for Docker -based containerised environment.
- Project managed development of an internal deployment tool which used **blue-green deployment strategy** for one of the complex products reducing frequency of failed deployments substantially.
- Developed monitoring and alert system for non-cloud apple hardware using Python and AWS services.
- Reduced peak traffic issues by 30% having shared expertise in locust load testing tool.
- Delivered 40% reduction in costs by removing multi-region AWS region implementation to **multi-AZ** to achieve **High Availability**.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE AND ACHIEVEMENTS continued

Maxis Sdn Bhd

DevOps Lead (promoted from Solutions Architect in 2018 and Mobile Apps Specialist in 2017)

2016-2019

Well known for deep knowledge and understanding of complex architectures and cloud paradigm. Was promoted multiple times in a short tenure due to quick learning and right mindset for scalable solutions.

Key achievements

- Adopted a consultative approach to analyse and transform functional requirements into technical solutions while building robust development team and stakeholder relationships.
- Led 12 team members to overcome challenges during transition from on-premises to cloud-based solution hosting on AWS
- Managed requirements elicitation and SCRUM framework to efficiently allocate tasks and resources
- Reduced the deployment time from 65 minutes to 7 minutes using AWS managed services which improved release confidence of business
- Implemented application monitoring system to secure live crash reports and analysis using Dynatrace

GOODCORE SOFTWARE, INC

Senior Software Engineer

2015-2016

Heavily involved in stakeholder management for requirement gathering, pitching solutions and architecture design of applications. Clients included International Bank, Energy provider corporation and Government Agencies of Malaysia. Successfully implemented security and scalability to meet compliances for financial applications with millions of users.

Systems Ltd

Managed a team of experienced engineers to utilise cutting edge technology in developing mobile applications. Contributed to implement agile mindset which reduced development time. Created applications for clients from Gulf region.

FOLIO3 PVT LTD

Senior Software Engineer (promoted from Software Engineer in 2013)

2011-2014

Developed enterprise level Mobile Applications and games mostly serving America and Canada markets. Created a first ever Special Interest Guild (SIG) in the organisation to focus on custom frameworks for mobile games.

EDUCATION AND QUALIFICATIONS

ASIA PACIFIC UNIVERSITY MALAYSIA | STAFFORDSHIRE UNIVERSITY UK

Master's in Science (Software Engineering) 2020

- Developed qualities to manage enterprise application development demands
- Studied various process methodologies and complex architecture design practices
- Gather visibility of quality requirements of large and distributed systems
- Got **Distinction** for my thesis on the topic of Microservice Architecture

FAST-NUCES PAKISTAN

Bachelor's in Science (Computer Science)

2011

- Gained hands-on experience on fundamental software engineering tools and techniques
- Studied and analysed issues and concerns involved in high-level software management
- Improved awareness of human-computer interaction (HCI) and how to develop sound criteria 'user friendliness'

Community Contributions

Pakistan

- IOS APPLICATION DEVELOPMENT WORKSHOP FAST NUCES 2011
- Mobile Devices future and Development Workshop IBA (Karachi) 2011
- GAMES DEVELOPMENT TALK IBA (KARACHI) 2012
- IOS APPLICATIONS AND GAME DEVELOPMENT LECTURE FAST NUCES 2012
- Webinar on Intro to Cloud and Free Website Hosting on AWS Online, FAST NUCES 2020
- Introduction to Serverless and Hands-on Lab on AWS Lambda AWS Community Pakistan 2020
- Serverless Cloud Computing University of Central Punjab (UCP) <u>Summer Talk Series September 2021</u>
- MENTOR IN AI/ML REACTOR BY AMAZON WEB SERVICES (AWS) AND EPIPHANY SEP/OCT 2021

Malaysia

- SRE PRACTICES IN MOBILE ENGINEERING <u>DEVOPS MEETUP MALAYSIA 2019</u>
- BAR CAMP CYBERJAYA MMU CYBERJAYA 2020
- CLOUDFORMATION TO TERRAFORM AND BEYOND AWS USER GROUP MALAYSIA 2020

ONLINE

- Core contributor of Software Development Pakistan (http://softdevpk.com)
- ADMIN AND CONTRIBUTOR IN AWS USER GROUP PAKISTAN (HTTPS://www.facebook.com/groups/awsugpk)
- ADMIN AND CONTRIBUTOR IN KARACHI FREELANCERS (<u>HTTPS://www.facebook.com/groups/karachifreelancers</u>)
- YouTube Channel All about Cloud (https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCOnAN556- JexfiOi9SgN g)